A Finding Aid to the Lilian Swann Saarinen Papers, circa 1909-1977, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Project Files, 1931-1966; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 5-6, 8, OVs 17-19
  - Oversized Evanston, Illinois, Post Office scanned with Box 5, Folder 54, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
  - Oversized KLM Airlines Sculpture, JFK Airport scanned with Box 5, Folder 61, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
  - Oversized Northland Center, Detroit, Michigan scanned with Box 5, Folder 66, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
  - Oversized Toffenetti's Restaurant, Chicago, Illinois, Sketches and Metal Cut-Out scanned with Box 5, Folder 75, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 19)
- Teaching Files, 1966-1970; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 6
  This series consists of three folders relating to a course Saarinen taught at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and the Cambridge Art Center entitled "The Language of Clay." Found are correspondence and memoranda, course descriptions, notes, and student rosters.
  - Language of Clay Course, Cambridge Art Center, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Language of Clay Course, M. I. T., 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Language of Clay Course, M. I. T., 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Financial Records, 1940s-1970s; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 6
  Series consists of invoices and receipts for supplies and other art-related expenses, records of book royalties for Who Am I? from Reynal & Hitchcock, Inc., and miscellaneous receipts. Also found are records documenting exhibition related expenses, and two catalogs for 1944 and 1956 Saarinen exhibitions, marked with prices.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned with the exception of routine financial records such as receipts.
  - Exhibition Sales and Expenses, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Invoices and Receipts, 1940s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Printed Material, circa 1930s-1970s; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 6
  Series includes announcements and catalogs for two Saarinen exhibitions, as well as some for other artists, many of which are annotated with comments by Saarinen stating her opinion of the artist featured. Also found are copies of a book jacket for The Americans: A New History of the People of the United States (Little Brown and Company, 1963) by Oscar Handlin, the jacket design for which includes a photo of a brass eagle by Saarinen.
  Printed material also includes a group of reference files of clippings, primarily featuring photos of animals, arranged alphabetically by animal, some news clippings about Saarinen and the Saarinen family, and a folder of news articles on miscellaneous subjects of interest to Saarinen.
  - Announcements and Catalogs, Saarinen, 1944-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Announcements and Catalogs, Other Artists, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Announcements and Catalogs, Other Artists, circa 1950s-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - News Clippings, 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - News Clippings About Saarinen and Family, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Reference Material Index, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Reference Material, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    - Bats, Bears, Birds, Buffalo, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Cats, Cougar, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Deer, Donkeys, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Dogs, circa 1920s-circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Dogs, circa 1920s-circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Dogs, circa 1920s-circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Elephants, Elk, Flowers, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Giant Pandas, Giraffes, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Horses, Insects, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Koala Bears, Lions, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Mice, Monkeys, Mountain Goats, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Okapi, Opossum, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Pekingese, Pigs, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Raccoons, Reptiles, Rhinoceroses, Squirrels, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Tigers, Wolves, Woodchucks, Zebra, "Rare Beasts", circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Scrapbooks, circa 1909-1974; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Boxes 6, 9
  Series includes a family scrapbook of clippings about Saarinen's father, Dr. Arthur Swann, concerning his bee cures for rheumatism, as well as his marriage to Saarinen's mother, Susan Sedgwick.
  The Saarinen scrapbook compiles letters, telegrams, news clippings, announcements and other printed material documenting Saarinen's career from 1935-1974.
  - Family Scrapbook, circa 1909; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Saarinen Scrapbook, 1935-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 32)
    Oversized volume housed in Box 9, Folder 1
  - Oversized Saarinen Scrapbook from Box 6, Folder 32, Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Artwork, circa 1920s-circa 1960s; Series 10; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 6-7, 9-10, OVs 20-27
  Artwork consists of Saarinen's sketches in graphite, crayon, ink, pastel, and watercolor that did not appear to be arranged as part of her project files. It includes early sketches dating from her childhood to her college years, and subsequent sketches from the 1940s-1960s, and illustrates her early and developing interest in animal subjects.
  Sketches are primarily of animals such as eagles, lions and other cats (including the Jungle Book character Bagheera), horses, Pekingese dogs, pelicans, and squirrels. Also found are sketches of various other animals including buffalo, bulls, calves, cats, dogs, goats, lambs, and pigs; anatomy and figure sketches; and a series of sketches executed on a trip to Mexico in 1938.
  One folder consists of six colored sketches of a Cambridge house by Mary L. Provost.
  - Abstract Sketches, circa 1945-circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 33)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 2 and OV 20
  - Anatomy Sketches, circa 1929-1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 34)
    Oversized material housed in OV 20
  - Animal Prints, circa 1930s-1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Animal Sketches, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    - Animals, Various, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Animals, Various, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 37)
      Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 3
    - Animals, Various, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Animals, Various, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 39)
      Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folders 3-5, Box 10, Folders 1-2, and OVs 20, 21
    - Eagles, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Eagles, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Eagles, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Eagles, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Eagles, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Eagles, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 45)
      Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folders 3-4, and OV 22
    - Horses, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Horses, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 47)
      Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 5
    - Horses, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Lions and Other Cats, 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 49)
      Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 6
    - Lions and Other Cats, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Lions and Other Cats, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 51)
      Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folders 6 -7 and OVs 23-24
    - Pekingese, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Pekingese, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Pekingese, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 54)
      Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 8
    - Pelicans, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Pelicans, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 56)
      Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 9
    - Polar Bear, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Skunk, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Squirrels, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Striped Tiger Couple, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Three-Toed Sloth, circa 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Figure and Head Sketches, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Figure and Head Sketches, circa 1930s-circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 63)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folders 10-12 and OV 25-26
  - Future Sculpture Ideas, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 64)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 13
  - Jewelry Designs, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Line Drawings, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Mexico Trip Sketches, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Mexico Trip Sketches, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Sketches and Notes, circa 1920s-circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Sketches and Notes, circa 1920s-circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Oversized material housed in Box 10, Folder 14
  - Mowgli, Bagheera and Baloo Sketches, circa 1936-1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Oversized material housed in OV 27
  - "Sketch for Dead Chamois", circa 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Drawings by Mary L. Provost of Cambridge House and Fabric, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Abstract Sketches scanned with Box 6, Folder 33, Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Animals, Various scanned with Box 6, Folders 37 and 39, Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Animals, Various scanned with Box 6, Folder 39, Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
    - Animals, Various scanned with Box 6, Folder 39, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Eagles scanned with Box 6, Folder 45, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
    - Horses scanned with Box 6, Folders 47-48, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Lions and Other Cats scanned with Box 6, Folders 49 and 51, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
    - Pekingese scanned with Box 6, Folder 54, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Pelicans scanned with Box 6, Folder 56, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Figure and Head Sketches scanned with Box 6, Folder 63, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10-12)
  - Oversized Future Sculpture Ideas scanned with Box 6, Folder 64, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Oversized Miscellaneous Sketches scanned with Box 7, Folder 4, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Oversized Abstract Sketches scanned with Box 6 Folder 33, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 20)
  - Oversized Anatomy Sketches scanned with Box 6, Folder 34, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 20)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Animals, Various scanned with Box 6, Folder 39, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 20)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Animals, Various scanned with Box 6, Folder 39, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 21)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Eagles scanned with Box 6, Folder 45, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 22)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Lions and Other Cats scanned with Box 6, Folder 51, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 23)
  - Oversized Animal Sketches, Lions and Other Cats scanned with Box 6, Folder 51, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 24)
  - Oversized Figure and Head Sketches scanned with Box 6, Folder 63, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 25)
  - Oversized Figure and Head Sketches scanned with Box 6, Folder 63, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 26)
  - Oversized Mowgli, Bagheera and Baloo Sketches scanned with Box 7, Folder 5, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 27)
- Photographs, circa 1940s, 1977; Series 11; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 7, 11, OV 27
  Photos of Saarinen and others include a negative of a photograph of Saarinen, possibly with Eero Saarinen, included with a 1977 letter of transmittal; a group photograph including Lilian, Eero and Eliel Saarinen with the model for the Detroit Civic Center; and a photo of an unidentified woman on a city street.
  Photos of artwork by Saarinen include animal sculpture, head and figure sculpture, wood carvings, and Saarinen's Mowgli and Bagheera sculpture. Also found are photos by Betty Cooper of Saarinen's 1944 exhibition at G Place Gallery.
  Series is scanned in entirety with the exception of blank versos of photographs and duplicates.
  - Photos of Saarinen and Others, circa 1940s, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Photos of Artwork, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - Animals, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Figures and Heads, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 3
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1930s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
      Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 4
    - Wood Carvings for Garden Posts, circa 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
      Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 5
  - Photos of Exhibition Installation, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 6
  - Oversized Photos of Artwork, Archival Resource Key (Box 11)
    - Animals scanned with Box 7, Folder 9, Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Figures and Heads scanned with Box 7, Folder 10, Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous scanned with Box 7, Folder 11, Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Wood Carvings for Garden Posts scanned with Box 7, Folder 12, Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Photos of Exhibition Installation scanned with Box 7, Folder 13, Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Photos of Artwork, Animals scanned with Box 7, Folder 9, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 27)